Melvin Abraham

Email: melvincomputing@outlook.com GitHub: https://github.com/mabraham123

LinkedIn: https://uk.linkedin.com/in/melvin-abraham-computing

I am a 4th year Computing student looking for a future in cyber security research. I am passionate about security, especially creating solutions that make security more usable to the general public.

Computing Related Work Experience

Intern Cyber Security Research: Heriot-Watt University

July 2020 - October 2020

Created a web app using Angular to collect account structure data used to analyse how protected a specific person's valuable accounts are under potential attack scenarios. Another responsibility was to create designs maintaining the privacy and anonymity of participants, keeping personal data and sensitive data separate. This project has allowed me to read up on academic research on user authentication and identity management, learn new technologies and to apply rapid prototyping methodologies.

To see the code: click here

Information Security Lab Tutor: University of Dundee

October 2020 - Dec 2020

I was responsible for multiple weekly technical labs for 80+ students. As part of this role, I created video content explaining cyber security concepts such as: encryption, web attacks, virus creation/detection and modular arithmetic. I taught students complex concept of the module one to one such as symmetric/asymmetric encryption, protocols, hashing and passwords.

Education

Applied Computing BSc (Hons) (Predicted First)

University of Dundee (4th year) graduating in 2021

Modules Include:

- Users and Interfaces UX/UI I gathered requirements using qualitative research methods (interviews/focus groups) then subsequently designed accessible and usable interfaces for underrepresented population groups.
- Object-Oriented Design and Development I created a full design specification for a game
 using OOP design principles/patterns in UML within the context of different
 methodologies such as Waterfall and Agile.
- **Multi Paradigm Programming** I created data structures from first principles such as Linked Lists, Queues and Hash Tables in C and C++ with emphasis on error checking and defensive programming.
- *Information Security* I studied applied cryptography, web security, security protocols and learned principles of secure software development.

High School (Highers) AAAB

St Augustine's RC High School, Edinburgh Graduated 2017

Kev Skills

My main language is **Python.** I also have experience in:

- C#/C++/C
- HTML/CSS/CSS Frameworks
- SQL/MySql /PHP
- Java / Scala

- Git/BASH
- JS/TypeScript/JS Frameworks
- PHP
- UML/Prototyping

Notable Projects

- Login System and Penetration Testing I worked as part of a software development team
 to create two login systems in C++. One system was secure with no vulnerabilities and
 one had a hidden obfuscated backdoor allowing entry into the system. I conducted
 penetration testing on other login systems from the class to find vulnerabilities that could
 be exploited.
- Accessible User Centred Website— Using a rapid prototyping environment to create a
 high-fidelity website prototype for clients who lack experience using computers.
 Qualitative techniques such as focus groups and interviews were used to understand the
 user clearly and what their specific needs were to aid how best we could design for them.
- Protecting Older Adults Online My Honours Project works to improve the resilience of older adults towards cyber-security attacks by developing methods to communicate account security weaknesses and advising on appropriate protections, through novel visualizations. For more detail: click here

Other Computing Related Experience

President of Dundee University Computing Society (DUCS)

I lead a team of students to create social and technical events for the collective Dundee Computing Student body. I have increased membership of this society from 30 to 200+ members and have increased the number of activities that the society organises. My aim has been to create a positive and effective environment within my team, to run events that bring students and members of industry together. Events included skills workshops with speakers from the university along with experts from industry, social events working with local businesses around Dundee, Coding challenges with external tech companies and our own annual Hackathon. My role includes:

Project Management

Public Speaking

Events Coordinating

Long term planning

Outreach

Leadership

Awards: Most Progressive Society- DUSA Annual Awards 2020

Strathmore Trophy Mentor

I guided 16 teams of secondary school pupils to come up with accessible designs for those who struggle speaking. I advised on accessible design and helped refine the ideas phase to come up with a realistic product to submit for judging.

STEM Ambassador

Other Work Experience

• Royal Air Force (Reserve): Officer Cadet with ESUAS

Sept 2017 - Aug 2020

I am responsible for maintenance and upkeep of communication channels for a squadron of 90 people. I have attended leadership courses which were applied in events planning and exercises to achieve mission goals. This has taught me determination, to think clearly under high pressure situations and contingency planning for when things do not go to plan.

University of Dundee: Student Ambassador

Jun 2018 - Present

This role requires me to lead people and manage visitors to make sure they get the best experience possible specifically tailored to them. This role has taught me how to communicate effectively, especially to external stakeholders.